{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "This man shared power with Nikolai Podgorny and Alexander Kosygin in the early years of his leadership, and his poor economic planning led to the beginning of the Era of Stagnation. This leader joined Jimmy Carter in signing the SALT II accords. He justified military intervention to protect communism in a namesake doctrine. For ten points, name this Soviet General Secretary who succeeded Nikita Khrushchev.",
      "answer": "Leonid Brezhnev"
    },
    {
      "question": "This country’s Catatumbo River has more lightning than anywhere else on Earth. A brackish inlet in this country was home to a 1914 oil discovery and an 1823 naval battle that earned this country’s independence from Spain. This country is home to the tallest waterfall in the world, Angel Falls, and the mouth of the Orinoco River. Lake Maracaibo is found in, for ten points, what South American country where a “Bolivarian Revolution” was led by Hugo Chavez?",
      "answer": "Bolivarian Republic of Venezuela"
    },
    {
      "question": "A campaign against these people began when Galerius was told that their existence prevented the Oracle at Delphi from speaking. The catacombs of Rome were predominantly used for the burial of these people. Though these people suffered the Diocletianic Persecution and Nero blamed them for causing the Great Fire, they were eventually granted legal status in the 313 AD Edict of Milan. For ten points, name this monotheistic faith adopted by Constantine the Great.",
      "answer": "Christians"
    },
    {
      "question": "A theme in Mozart’s twenty-fifth piano concerto is sometimes cited as this song’s source. Pyotr Lavrov wrote a “worker’s” version of this song, which was originally written by Claude Rouget de Lisle as “War Song for the Rhine Army.” A musical depiction of the Battle of Borodino juxtaposes this song with “God Save The Tsar.” This song was quoted in Tchaikovsky’s 1812 Overture, where it represents Napoleon’s army. For ten points, name this revolutionary song, the national anthem of France.",
      "answer": "La Marseillaise"
    },
    {
      "question": "This organization was criticized for being unable to control the Orange Riots. Charles Murphy tried to reform this organization, which supported Al Smith for President in 1928. Jimmy Hines was unable to stop this organization’s defeat by Fiorello LaGuardia. A leader of this organization was targeted by Samuel Tilden and depicted with a bag of money for a head by Thomas Nast. For ten points, name this Democratic political machine in New York City that was dominated by Boss Tweed.",
      "answer": [
        "Tammany Hall or the Society of St. Tammany",
        "the Sons of St. Tammany",
        "the Columbian Order"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This organization used a code called PURPLE to conceal diplomatic messages. This organization built a fortress at Rabaul and was the target of the Great Turkey Shoot. This military force defeated Force Z, consisting of the Prince of Wales and the Repulse, which had been sent to reinforce Malaya. Its forces were concentrated in the Combined Fleet, which suffered the loss of four aircraft carriers at the Battle of Midway. For ten points, name this military force that fought America in the Pacific Ocean during World War II.",
      "answer": [
        "Imperial Japanese Navy",
        "IJN",
        "Combined Fleet until mentioned",
        "descriptive answers"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "After rising to power, this group banned the practice of “Bacha Bazi” between Pashtun warlords. Some former supporters of this group have defected to ISIs’s Khorasan Province branch. In March 2001, this group demolished giant, centuries-old statues of the Buddha in Bamiyan Province; later in 2001, this group was ousted from power by a NATO-led coalition. For ten points, name this Sunni terrorist group that operates in Afghanistan.",
      "answer": "Taliban"
    },
    {
      "question": "This President won the presidency thanks to James Birney’s Liberty Party sapping his opponent’s anti-slavery support in states like New York. He died just three months after leaving office, a record for shortest Presidential retirement. This man is the only President to have once been Speaker of the House. Supporters of this “dark horse” winner chanted “54-40 or fight!” in endorsing his policy of expansionism. For ten points, name this U.S. President during the Mexican-American War.",
      "answer": "James Knox Polk"
    },
    {
      "question": "A character in this play claims that a sunburn could not make his face any worse looking. In this play, it is said that Arthur’s bosom is the destination of the dead Falstaff. At a charge at Harfleur, this play’s title character declares “Once more unto the breach,” and later uses the phrase “we few, we happy few, we band of brothers” to open the St. Crispin’s Day Speech. For ten points, name this Shakespeare history play about the British king who won the Battle of Agincourt.",
      "answer": "Henry V do not"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man claimed that there were 400 neatly marked graves because one soldier slept. As part of Operation Fortitude, this man was assigned command of the fictitious First U.S Army Group. This general led the breakout from Normandy and the relief of the garrison of Bastogne during the Battle of the Bulge, but was relieved of command after two slapping incidents in North Africa and Sicily. For ten points, name this aggressive commander of the American Third Army during World War II.",
      "answer": "George S. Patton Jr."
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "An early action during this conflict was the capture of Government House in Stanley. This conflict began on the orders of Leopoldo Galtieri, who lost power as a result. During this war, Exocet missiles were able to destroy the Sheffield, and the Conqueror was able to sink the General Belgrano. This war’s outcome hastened the fall of a military junta while strengthening Margaret Thatcher’s government. For ten points, name this 1982 war between Argentina and Britain over a South Atlantic archipelago.",
        "answer": "Falklands War"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Argentine military junta that collapsed shortly after the Falklands War came to power during this period of state terrorism in Argentina, during which the Mothers of the Plaza de Mayo protested the kidnapping of “disappeared persons.”",
        "answer": [
          "Dirty War or Guerra Sucia",
          "Process of National Reorganization"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Two answers required. During an election contested between these two men, the endorsement of John Crittenden swung the election to the winner. A speech by one of these men was used to begin the other’s Cooper Union speech, given to elaborate his views by invoking the Founding Fathers. One of these men issued the Freeport Doctrine, articulating his support for popular sovereignty, during a series of senatorial debates between these two men in 1858. For ten points, name these two Illinois politicians, who finished first and fourth in the Presidential election of 1860.",
        "answer": "Abraham Lincoln and Stephen Douglas BONUS:Duringthedebates,Douglaswasheavilyquestionedabouthissupportforthispieceoflegislation, which repealed the Missouri Compromise. ANSWER: Kansas-Nebraska Act 3 Sculptures of caryatids were used in place of these structures in the Erechtheion on the Athenian acropolis. A temple at Karnak includes enormous examples of these structures decorated with hieroglyphs in its hypostyle courtyard. Their capitals can be decorated with various objects, including acanthus leaves on the top of the Corinthian type. For ten points, name these architectural elements that often bear the weight of a roof. ANSWER: columns"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Corinthian columns are the most ornate of the three ancient order; this simplest of the three was characterized by plain capitals, funnel-like shapes, and no bases.",
        "answer": "Doric order"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man’s reputation suffered when two dozen miners were killed in a firefight at his Ludlow colony. Charles Pratt and Henry Rogers decided to work with this man after their companies were priced out in the “Cleveland Massacre.” When this man’s monopoly was found to be in violation of the Sherman Antitrust Act, it was split into companies that became Exxon and Mobil. For ten points, name this wealthiest American of all time, the founder of the Standard Oil Company.",
        "answer": "John D. Rockefeller"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Rockefeller’s underhanded pricing tactics were exposed by this muckraker, who published The History of the Standard Oil Company in McClure’s magazine.",
        "answer": "Ida Tarbell"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This leader called a Congress of Berlin in order to override the Treaty of San Stefano. He supported Lord Derby’s attempts to pass a Reform Act prohibiting rotten boroughs. This leader’s foreign policies included buying out the Suez Canal Company and ordering a failed invasion of Afghanistan as part of the Great Game with Russia. This politician was a favorite of Queen Victoria and crowned her Empress of India. For ten points, name this Conservative prime minister of Great Britain and rival of William Gladstone.",
        "answer": "Benjamin Disraeli"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Disraeli began his political career as a supporter of this prominent Conservative, but eventually opposed him over his repeal of the Corn Laws. This man, who employed William Gladstone in his cabinet, created the first English police force.",
        "answer": "Sir Robert Peel"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A man undergoing this event was told, “Play the man, Master Ridley.” Many people who were suspected of holding “Thyestean banquets” endured this action, to which Pierre de Lancre subjected many Basques. Carbon monoxide poisoning was a common fate for subjects of this action. A military commander who successfully lifted the Siege of Orleans died via, for ten points, what method of execution for Joan of Arc?",
        "answer": [
          "burning at the stake",
          "being burnt alive",
          "execution by public burning, etc."
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This Czech reformer was burned at the stake during the Council of Constance, despite Emperor Sigismund’s promise of safe passage and conduct.",
        "answer": "Jan Hus or John Huss"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The monarchy in this region was replaced by a republic after the Anif declaration. This region was united with the Palatinate by Charles Theodore and acquired new territory after the Treaty of Pressburg with Napoleon. A duchy in this region was ruled by the Wittelsbachs and led the Counter-Reformation as a bastion of Catholicism. Its “Mad King,” Ludwig II, built Neuschwanstein [noysh-van-stein] castle in this region and allied with Austria against Prussia. For ten points, name this southern region of Germany, governed from Munich.",
        "answer": "Bavaria"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In 1923, Hitler attempted to lead a coup from this type of building in Munich. He was arrested and sent to prison, where he wrote Mein Kampf.",
        "answer": [
          "beer hall",
          "the Bu¨rgerbr¨aukeller",
          "the Beer Hall Putsch"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "An invasion of this country began shortly after Robert Paz was shot on his way to dinner in the El Chorrillo [chore-ee-oh] neighborhood. Loud rock music was used to flush a leader of this country out of the Vatican embassy, where he had taken refuge. In an attempt to stop drug trafficking in this country, George H.W. Bush authorized military intervention in Operation Just Cause in 1989. For ten points, name this Central American country from which Manuel Noriega was removed from power.",
        "answer": "Panama"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The U.S. Army tried to bring Manuel Noriega to his “sha-na-na-na na-na-na-na na-na-na-na knees, knees” [sha, 11 “na”s, 2 knees] with this Guns n’ Roses song, whose opening line notes “We got fun and games.”",
        "answer": "Welcome to the Jungle"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "Organized Labor in the US",
      "prompt": "In the history of organized labor in America, what...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Industry’s workers were led by Walter Reuther in the UAW?",
          "answer": [
            "automotive industry",
            "car manufacturing"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Number of hours in a workday was won by unions, creating the forty-hour workweek?",
          "answer": "eight-hour day"
        },
        {
          "question": "Union merged with the Congress of Industrial Organizations, or CIO, in 1955?",
          "answer": "AFL"
        },
        {
          "question": "Does the “I” stand for in the name of the William Heywood’s, union, the IWW?",
          "answer": [
            "industrial",
            "Industrial Workers of the World"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "President’s veto was overridden by Congress to pass the union-restricting Taft-Hartley Act?",
          "answer": "Harry Truman"
        },
        {
          "question": "Union was led by Terence Powderly and Uriah Stephens and peaked in the 1880s?",
          "answer": [
            "Knights of Labor",
            "KoL",
            "K of L"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Objects were produced by an International Union once led by Samuel Gompers?",
          "answer": "cigars"
        },
        {
          "question": "Type of contract, forbidding union membership, was outlawed by the Norris-LaGuardia Act?",
          "answer": "yellow-dog contracts"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Justinian the Great",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Empire that Justinian ruled, which grew out of the Eastern Roman Empire.",
          "answer": "Byzantine Empire"
        },
        {
          "question": "Religious official appointed by Justinian, the head of the Roman Catholic Church.",
          "answer": "pope or Bishop of Rome"
        },
        {
          "question": "Church built in Constantinople by Justinian. Converted to a mosque after the Ottoman conquest, it sits next to the Blue Mosque.",
          "answer": "Hagia Sophia"
        },
        {
          "question": "African city reconquered by Justinian from the Vandals, once the capital of Rome’s rival for the Mediterranean.",
          "answer": "Carthage"
        },
        {
          "question": "Riots that nearly toppled Justinian after a series of chariot races got out of hand.",
          "answer": "Nika Riots"
        },
        {
          "question": "Region ruled by Justinian’s rival, the Sassanid Empire, from their cities in Ctesiphon [tess-ih-fon] and Esfahan.",
          "answer": [
            "Persia",
            "Parthia"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Influential wife of Justinian, who rose from being an actress to Empress.",
          "answer": "Theodora"
        },
        {
          "question": "General employed by Justinian to conquer Italy, before his eventual disgrace and begging on the streets of Rome.",
          "answer": "Belisarius"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Hong Kong",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Country that currently controls the territory of Hong Kong.",
          "answer": "People’s Republic of China"
        },
        {
          "question": "Country that leased Hong Kong from the Qing [ching] Dynasty.",
          "answer": [
            "United Kingdom or UK",
            "Great Britain",
            "England"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Conflicts that forced the Qing to give up Hong Kong, fought over an addictive drug.",
          "answer": "Opium Wars"
        },
        {
          "question": "Item that provided protection from tear gas as well as rain during a namesake 2014 movement in Hong Kong.",
          "answer": [
            "Umbrella Revolution",
            "any particular color, though the symbol of the movement is a yellow umbrella"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Nearby former Portuguese colony that, like Hong Kong, is a Special Administrative Region.",
          "answer": "Macau"
        },
        {
          "question": "Animal nickname for Hong Kong, as well as Taiwan, Singapore, and South Korea, for their rapid economic booms.",
          "answer": "Four Asian Tigers"
        },
        {
          "question": "Densely populated settlement in Kowloon that was a home of lawlessness until its 1993 demolition.",
          "answer": "Kowloon Walled City"
        },
        {
          "question": "City that borders Hong Kong on the mainland. It was the first Special Economic Zone.",
          "answer": "Shenzhen"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This work claims that religion is necessary to support political prosperity and notes that “the jealousy of a free people ought to be constantly awake” against the “insidious wiles of foreign influence.” This work draws an analogy between the interdependence of the (20 pts)",
        "north to south and east to west, arguing that decisions must be made as one nation. This speech cautions against the influence of European foreign powers and of the dangers of (10 pts)",
        "political parties. For ten points, name this work, which was published rather than delivered as a speech, near the end of the first U.S. president’s term."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "George Washington’s Farewell Address",
        "descriptive answers"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Two answers required. The fleets of these two nations joined up to defeat Andrea Doria at Ponza. Fears of Habsburg expansion after Charles V’s capture of Tunis led (20 pts)",
        "Jean de la Forest to negotiate a military treaty between these two nations. These two nations faced each other in the Battle of the Pyramids during the Egyptian campaign, which marked the end of the 1536 (10 pts)",
        "“Unholy Alliance” signed by Francis I and Suleiman the Magnificent. For ten points, name these two European empires, led by Napoleon and Sultan Selim III."
      ],
      "answer": "France and the Ottoman Empire"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Subsections of this archipelago include the Islands of Four Mountains and the Fox Islands. This island chain is geologically related to the Commander Islands, and its indigenous people refer to themselves as (20 pts)",
        "Unangan. Fort Mears and the naval base at Dutch Harbor were bombed by the Japanese during this archipelago’s namesake campaign, which saw the capture of two islands and the only fighting on (10 pts)",
        "North American soil during World War II. Attu is part of, for ten points, what Alaskan island chain?"
      ],
      "answer": "Aleutian Islands"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) James Frazer used the post-hoc fallacy to explain the development of this concept in early culture. Marcel Mauss and Henri Hubert developed a sociological theory of this phenomenon which claimed that it was the “private” manifestation of (20 pts)",
        "religion. Ralph Merrifield first defined this concept in anthropology as the use of practices intended to harness the occult. This concept was described in (10 pts)",
        "“Coral Gardens” in a Bronislaw Malinowski work about these beliefs in the Trobriand Islands. For ten points, name this idea that rituals, actions, and symbols can be used to exploit the supernatural, supposedly performed by wizards."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "magic broadly",
        "similar answers, like wizardry, sorcery, casting spells, etc."
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) For his efforts during an attempt at this action, Michel Ney was dubbed the “bravest of the brave.” The truce of Deulino ended a successful instance of this action, which included the Battle of (20 pts)",
        "Klushino. A leader fled to the Ottoman Empire after the Great Frost of 1709 doomed an attempt at this action, which ended with a defeat for Adam Leuwenhaupt. A failed attempt at this action was doomed by scorched earth tactics, (10 pts)",
        "Cossacks, and “General Winter.” For ten points, name this difficult military action that Napoleon attempted in 1812."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "invading Russia",
        "elaborations involving French, Polish, and/or Swedish invasions of Russia"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Olefin polymerization can be catalyzed by compounds containing this metal that are named for Ziegler and Natta. In 1888, Karl Josef Bayer developed a process for refining the oxide of this element from (20 pts)",
        "bauxite; the smelting of this element is then typically done through the electrolytic Hall-H´eroult process. This element is the most common metal found in the Earth’s (10 pts)",
        "crust and is crucial for aerospace technology. For ten points, name this lightweight metal with atomic number 13 that is used in soda cans."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "aluminum",
        "Al"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) An early proponent of this cause was mayor Neal Dow, who crafted the short-lived Maine Law. Wayne Wheeler pioneered “pressure politics” in support of this cause. Another advocate for this cause was known for using a (20 pts)",
        "hatchet to destroy contraband. The Volstead Act provided legal backing to this cause, which was supported by (10 pts)",
        "Carrie A. Nation and a Women’s Christian Union. For ten points, name this cause that became national policy with the passing of the 18th Amendment, then was revoked with the 21st Amendment."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "temperance or prohibition of alcohol",
        "descriptive answers that relate to the banning of alcohol"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The Revolt of the Lankans took place in this colony among angry nobles called datus, who were divided into the Puno, Ginoo, and Maginoo. This colony was founded after the conquest of the Moro people and conflicts with (20 pts)",
        "Brunei and Sulu. Ships departing from this colony brought porcelain and china to Acapulco across the Pacific. The discoverer of this colony, (10 pts)",
        "Ferdinand Magellan, died here during the Battle of Mactan. For ten points, name this Spanish colony where galleons brought silver to the port of Manila."
      ],
      "answer": "Philippines or the Spanish East Indies"
    }
  ]
}